WWW.MY-SUBS.CO
I think we're all here. I'm
looking forward to this.
You should be at this board meeting.
You're a trustee and the patron.
- Why are they coming here?
- I don't know exactly.
I suppose they have something
they want to tell us.
They obviously need more money.
Right, we're off. See you later.
Who's that? It's not one of
the farmers' wives, is it?
No, I don't think so.
Do you really like riding like that?
When a side-saddle is
so much more graceful.
And so much more dangerous.
Is Mama right? You're dodging
the hospital meeting?
Only a little bit.
- May I be of assistance?
- No, thank you.
Well, I expect you'll want to get started.
- Started at what?
- Following the hunt.
If you go with the others, they'll show
you where to watch them jump the brook.
I see. Ta very much.
- Can I lick the bowl?
- Yes.
You can both lick the bowl.
- I enjoyed that.
- Was it your first meet?
There's not much hunting in Bayswater.
Andy, go back and check
that everything's come down.
- I think it has, Mrs Hughes.
- It never hurts to check.
- He's a nice boy.
- He is.
And I think I'm showing him
the right way to do things.
I should let him find
his own way, Mr Barrow.
Can I have a piggy-back?
All right, then, but not for long.
- I want to go hunting, too.
- All aboard.
- And off we go!
- Faster! Faster!
- Everything running smoothly?
- Oh, I suppose so.
But it's harder with no
kitchen maid, you know.
- Have you settled on a date yet?
- Date?
Oh, you mean for the wedding?
No, not yet.
Oh, what are you doing up here?
The button came off my cuff.
I thought I'd mend it
before things got busy.
- Shall we go down?
- Before we do...
.. I wish you'd tell me what's wrong.
Whatever makes you say that?
- You'll say I'm being stupid.
- Well, maybe you are.
Maybe.
You see, when I accepted Mr Carson...
- You didn't mean it?
- Oh, yes, I did.
He's a very, very dear man.
So, what's the problem?
I hadn't fully considered...
all the aspects of marriage.
Of what I was getting into.
I don't understand. What aspects?
You know each other better
than most couples at the start.
Oh, my Lord. You mean...?
Yes.
That is precisely what I mean.
Well, there's nothing so
terrible about it, is there?
So they say. I wouldn't know, of course.
Mrs Patmore, look at me. I'm
a woman in late middle age...
Oh, don't say 'late'.
I was not bad-looking as a
girl, if you can believe it.
- Very easily.
- But these days?
I'm not sure I can let
him see me as I am now.
Perhaps you can keep the lights off.
That is not helpful, Mrs Patmore.
Well, won't he feel the same?
I mean, no-one's clapped eyes on
him without his togs for years.
- Except the doctor.
- Good point. Very good point.
Maybe he'd prefer us to leave
that side of things alone.
Sorry? Live like brother
and sister, you mean?
A very loving brother and sister.
- And that's what you want?
- I don't know what I want.
Except not to feel embarrassed and absurd.
Is this why you've not fixed the date?
I think we should be clear
about what we're doing.
- Or not doing.
- Yes. Thank you, Mrs Patmore.
The trouble is, I don't believe it's
a conversation I can have with him...
Oh, you're not suggesting I try?
Oh, would you?
Oh, by 'eck!
I've had some commissions
in my time, but...
It would be such a weight off my mind.
Anna? Whatever's happened?
Nothing. I'm starting a cold.
I'd better get on.
Are you all right?
Of course. No bones broken, anyway.
Thanks to nice Mr Fairclough here.
Very kind of you, Fairclough.
Good to see you out.
I never like to miss a day's
hunt when it's on my doorstep.
- Shall I take you back to the
house, m'lady? - Certainly not.
If you can just give me a hand up.
I'm not taking any sort of 'tone'.
I'm just reminding you of the deadline.
Thank you. Goodbye.
Trouble at the mill?
My editor, Mr Skinner, again.
- What's the problem?
- Everything's a problem.
No, that's not quite true.
I think the problem is me.
He doesn't like working for
a woman. Simple as that.
I suppose you're right, not
selling up and taking the money.
I think I am.
Andrew, please ask Mrs
Hughes to organise tea for...
- I'm not sure. Can you count them
as they arrive? - Very good, m'lady.
- When did you learn about this?
- What do you mean?
Well, you seem to have all the facts,
when it's the first
time we've heard of it.
What does that matter?
The fact is that the Royal
Yorkshire County Hospital
wants to take over our little hospital,
which is outrageous.
- But it's not as simple as that.
- Why not?
Because there may be
benefits for the village.
If we form such a partnership,
our patients would have access
to more modern equipment,
to more advanced treatments.
Our fundraising would be more efficient.
And the price of the fundraising
would be to lose all control,
and to become the tools of a
faceless committee in York.
What matters more? Health or power?
What matters is to have power over
the maintenance of our own health.
- Ladies, ladies, please...
- Lady Grantham is right.
Our independence is not
something we should just abandon
without a second thought.
- How did you find out about this?
- They wrote to me.
Who did? I'm the hospital
Almoner. Nobody's written to me.
Ever since you took that position,
you talk as if you run the place.
I do run the place!
Or, at least, I know every
detail of how it's run.
And I ought to be told
about any proposed changes.
- You're being told now.
- If you must know, it was a friend,
on the board in York,
who whispered it to me.
They'll write to all of us soon.
So, you want to protect your power
at the expense of the patients.
I want to protect the patients
at the expense of my power.
And may the best man win.
I'm glad we agree on this.
Don't let's make too much of it.
I'm fine.
Good afternoon.
I'm going in.
I'm completely whacked.
Don't tell your mother.
Can you make sure he gets a
proper rub-down? He did well.
Yes, m'lady.
- Who are you?
- Rita Bevan.
Don't you know me, Lady
Mary? Cos I know you.
No. I do not know you.
And I suppose you have forgotten
the Grand Hotel in Liverpool, too, m'lady?
And your nights there
with Viscount Gillingham?
I was a chambermaid. But I suppose
we're invisible to people like you.
This is all nonsense. You've no proof.
Don't be silly. You
don't know what I've got.
To start with, I've got
a page from the register.
- Then you are a thief.
- Yes, I am a thief,
and I want a thousand pounds
to keep my mouth shut.
That's ridiculous.
We'll see how ridiculous it is.
I'm going now, but I'll be back.
Don't bother. You're not the first
person who's tried to blackmail me.
Well, I'm glad you know how it
works. And as I say, I will be back.
- Penny for your thoughts.
- They're not worth as much.
- They would be to me.
- Oh, I'm worn out. Give me some tea.
You let those children run you ragged.
Thank you. I've had Miss Marigold
on my back since luncheon.
- How lucky is that child?
- Why do you say that?
Well, what was she? A farmer's daughter.
Until she caught the eye of Lady Edith.
Now she'll grow up in the
bosom of a great family
and live her life accordingly.
I don't believe she has any
greater guarantee of happiness.
That's Lady Mary, back from the hunt.
I know you don't approve, but
it's quite ordinary in London now.
- Will that be all, my Lord?
- Yes, thank you.
At least... there is something.
This is part of a larger conversation,
but at some point we need to discuss
future staffing requirements at Downton.
We have cut down quite a bit, my Lord.
We've only got one hall
boy and two housemaids,
and as kitchen staff have
left, we've not replaced them.
I know, and there's no
need for anything drastic.
The estate's doing well, thanks
to Mr Crawley and Mr Branson,
but I don't like to feel out
of step with my fellow man.
As a matter of fact,
both the housemaids have
handed in their notice.
I was going to tell you.
- Oh. Were they unhappy? I hope not.
- No, no, no.
One is leaving to get married,
which we knew was coming,
and Madge has found a job in a shop.
Which is better than working here?
She says that her young man wants
her to be free in the evenings.
I must ask you to remember, my Lord,
that there were six footmen when I
first came here and five housemaids.
Now we've got to two of each
and no kitchen maids at all.
We must run this place
as it should be run.
I'm not asking you to wield a scythe,
but, I mean, who has an
under-butler these days?
If I could stop history in
its tracks, maybe I would.
- But I can't, Carson. Nor you, nor I
can hold back time. - Unfortunately.
The Dowager Countess has arrived, my Lord.
Hmm.
- She definitely waited on you?
- Well, she knows I was there
with Lord Gillingham.
- Are you going to pay her?
- A thousand pounds? Don't be mad.
If I pay her, she'll only come back.
- What will you do, then?
- Nothing, until I have to.
Why should a paper print it, anyway?
'Earl's daughter in love
tryst with married viscount'?
He wasn't married then. Nor was I.
It's still a good story.
Anyway, what about YOUR
story? Is there any more news?
You must still be on bail,
or else you'd have told me.
We both are, in a way. At least,
I'm on bail and he's on tenterhooks,
until they decide if they can
make a case against either of us.
- What does Sergeant Willis say?
- Nothing, and Mr Willis isn't unkind.
He'd have told us if it was over.
- No wonder you're upset.
- Why do you say that?
You just seemed a bit down in
the mouth, when you came in.
- Never mind me. Now, what shall
we do about your hair? - Mm.
You'll be very late going down.
I wouldn't have washed it, but I
came off, and it was full of mud.
You'll just have to do your best.
- You're very quiet.
- I've got a lot on my mind.
A problem shared is a problem halved.
Huh! Or doubled.
Ah, there you are.
They're down, Mrs Patmore -- I'll
announce it when you're ready.
No, I'm ready now. The first course
is cold, so it's already up there.
- Very good. - Oh, could I have a
word? When you're done for the night.
- May I know what about?
- I'll tell you then.
It's nothing bad. At least...
No, I'll tell you then.
Hm.
I don't think Mr Molesley meant
to be unkind about Miss Marigold.
I'm sure he didn't.
Only, it seemed to put
you in a strange mood.
Did it?
It's ironic.
So many children in need of a home,
and so many homes in need of a child.
My God, what have I said?
My darling, what have I said?
It's not your fault.
Only... I thought I was pregnant.
And then, this morning...
Well, anyway, now I'm not.
You should have told me.
I didn't want to get your hopes up.
You weren't to know that would happen.
But, you see, I was.
Because it's happened before. Twice.
I can't do it. I'm not able.
There is no proof of that.
But if you're not, you're not.
We'll be all right.
I've let you down.
There are no words less true than those.
You could never let me down.
Besides, we've had so many troubles.
There isn't a couple in the world
who've had as many worries as we have.
So, what did Tom have to say?
He's found a flat with a garden
and Sybbie's happy at her school.
- Speaking in an American accent.
- Would that be so awful?
Poor Tom. If he was a fish out of
water here, what is he in Boston?
A fish back in water, I'd have thought.
There's a tremendous
Irish community there.
If you ask me, he's landed on his feet.
How is the search going
for his replacement?
We've hardly started, really.
We haven't started at all.
We don't need a replacement.
- Why not?
- Because I'm his replacement.
- I'm going to be the new agent.
- You're what?
We've worked together since he came
back from Dublin. Why shouldn't I?
- Quite right.
- Yes, but what about the heavy lifting?
Granny, I think I can lift quite
as much as sad old Mr Jarvis,
before Matthew chased him away.
Brains count for more than muscles.
Long live women's rights and all that,
but it's not a good idea to
take on a job that wears you out.
- I'm doing it now, aren't I?
- Yes.
But you'll be dead by the
year's end at this rate.
I suppose we only know what we're
capable of when we test our limits.
And we certainly know
what you're capable of.
What is that supposed to mean?
Isobel, what's Granny done wrong?
We're to have a fight about the hospital,
and she began it by concealing the facts.
- Oh, dear. - It seems to me we should --
- Cora, don't waste your time on it.
It's a matter between
me and Cousin Isobel.
We can't have the President in a
tug-of-war against the Almoner.
We can if it's needed.
With poor old Clarkson as the rope.
Is now a good time?
As good as any. Sit.
- Some of this?
- No, thank you.
Erm... well...
The thing is, I've been speaking
to Mrs Hughes about your marriage.
- Oh, yes?
- And I was wondering about...
At least, we were both
discussing the terms
on which you intend to live.
Good terms, I hope...
- Are you sure?
- Go on, then.
You see, we were talking
of how it will be,
sharing your life after
so many years on your own.
That's the nub of it -- I agree.
Because you've got used to
doing things in a certain way.
It's true. I have.
But I like to think that
I'm not too old to change.
No, of course not.
But do you expect to... to share your...
- .. way of life?
- Doesn't everyone when they marry?
I suppose.
So, what can I do for you?
Nothing.
Oh... oh, it was very
nice, having a little chat.
And thank you for the port.
But I'll leave you to it now.
Hmm.
Are you plotting something?
You sound like a governess
in fear of dismissal.
You sound like a guilty party, who's
trying to throw me off the scent.
Is something on your mind, Robert?
You seem a bit troubled lately.
Do I? Well, maybe I am.
To be honest, I'm starting to ask myself
how much longer we can go on with it all.
- Well, go on with what?
- The household. The servants.
- You're not in
difficulties, are you? - No.
But a butler, under-butler,
footmen, a valet, ladies' maids...
to say nothing of the housemaids,
the kitchen, the laundry, the --
Yes, well, you...
you think it's a bit too much in 1925?
The wage bill is three times
what it was before the war.
Soon it will be worse. And anyway,
who lives as we used to, now?
Well, I don't think you'll
see much change at the Palace.
The Royal Family, then, the dukes,
some others, and good luck to them.
But most people are cutting down.
It seems hard that men and women
should lose their livelihoods
because it's gone out of fashion.
But what if they could find work?
Well, how many do you see going?
I don't know, but some.
Granny was on form.
I ought to go up to London soon.
- Is this your editor?
- Partly him.
I must get him back on track.
But my tenant's also moving
out at the end of the month.
- Out of Michael Gregson's flat?
- Out of MY flat.
But, anyway, I'm not
quite sure what to do.
Should I smarten it up
and let it out again?
Or would it be good for me
to have my own London base?
It's a thought.
Anyway, I'm off to bed. Good night.
Good night.
Edith alone on the town.
What will she get up to?
At her age, she's entitled
to get up to something.
- What's the matter?
- Why do you ask?
I... just worry about you.
I'm your father. It's allowed.
What makes you think
anything's the matter?
How was dinner? Did you enjoy it?
Quite. I'm afraid the times are
catching up with the Abbey, too,
as they were bound to, I suppose.
How do you mean, m'lady?
Well, the way they run things there.
They're not going to lay off staff?
- Don't say anything.
- Oh, I'm a veritable tomb
where other people's secrets
are concerned, m'lady.
- It won't affect us.
- I hope not.
Oh, no.
We're down to the bare bones, as it is.
You're right. Things are
positively frugal around here.
I do worry about those who'll have to go.
But remember, no talking.
M'lady.
- How did you get on last night?
- Oh...
Er... Daisy, fetch that coconut ice.
I'd like Mrs Hughes to try it.
Not very well. I couldn't
seem to get to the subject.
- Was he putting you off?
- No, I wouldn't say that.
But it was a difficult topic to arrive at.
Erm... excuse me. I hope you can help me.
I've got a message for
Lady Mary from the Dowager.
She said it's urgent.
If you give it to me, I'll
get someone to take it.
Lady Grantham said I was to
put it into Lady Mary's hand.
I'm sorry, Miss, but we don't know
you, and Lady Mary isn't down yet.
I'm Ellen Gorse. I've just
started at the Dower House.
I've only got to give her an envelope.
Very well. I'll take you to her room.
Yes?
Sorry to bother you,
m'lady, but the Dowager
has sent a message for you.
Apparently, it's urgent.
- I doubt it.
- I haven't got it, m'lady.
She sent a maid to put it into your hand.
How mysterious. Well,
where is this Mercury maid?
Here, m'lady.
Thank you, Mrs Hughes.
We mustn't delay you.
Can you send Anna up?
Of course, m'lady.
- How dare you?
- I dare more than you dare.
You could have asked her to
throw me out. Why didn't you?
It would only make things worse.
It'll be a lot worse when you're
sprawled over the centre pages
of the News Of The World.
You're revolting.
Can't you see that none of
that stuff works with me?
- What stuff?
- La-di-da, gracious great lady.
You think you're so marvellous, don't you?
Your lot's finished. You're
going down and we're coming up.
The working classes may be coming up,
but I'd be very surprised if you are.
Now, please get out.
- Can I have the money?
- No.
You'd only come back for more.
Suppose I gave you my word?
If I wasn't so disgusted,
that would make me laugh.
- I was just on my way up --
- This is Miss Bevan, whom I told you about.
- How did you get in here?
- How do you think? I lied.
Now, you've got one more chance,
and that'll be your last.
You must be a glutton for punishment.
Now, Anna, can you make sure she leaves?
Certainly, m'lady.
Mr Molesley's been on
at me about my exams.
Ooh, I don't envy you. I still
cheer myself up by thinking,
at least I don't have
to take any more exams.
But he's right. I must take
them, or what's it all been for?
Ooh, it doesn't look as if she'll
be staying on at the Dower House.
No. I wouldn't have said she
was a long-term prospect.
Not very congenial.
'Ey, I wonder what was in that message.
I suppose you're surprised to see
me lining up with the Dowager.
Only because I think you're wrong.
Well, you have a touching
faith in officialdom.
Once they take over the hospital,
they will lay down the law, with no
regard for the needs of this area.
I've seen it in war and in
peace -- it's always the same.
Do you not care?
I'll tell you what I care
about. It's not complicated.
I care about survival rates.
Mrs Crawley, I'm sure you
don't intend to be offensive...
No, but I intend to be
truthful. I'm the Almoner.
I know the facts about
this place as well as you.
So, this isn't something Lord
Merton has persuaded you into?
- Lord Merton?
- You remember him, surely?
That famous fount of
all medical knowledge.
Well, I wish you luck
with your fellow warrior.
What is it they say? Rather you than me.
Good day.
You've got a visitor. Sergeant Willis.
- What does he want?
- Search me. He's in Mr Carson's room.
Mr Bates is there already.
But surely, if a woman's
confessed, that's the end of it?
Not quite. Inspector Vyner thinks
it may be a false confession.
You do get people coming forward
who had nothing to do with it.
But haven't they checked her story?
If she's one of his victims,
people must have seen her with him.
That's the point. They
can't prove a connection.
She says Mr Green picked her up in a
pub, but no-one can corroborate it.
We can't send her to
prison if she's delusional.
- Then why have you come here?
- Because it's your right to know
that someone had confessed.
How did she know Mr Green
would be in Piccadilly?
It was a spur-of-the-moment thing.
She just saw him standing there.
Did he speak to her,
like the witness said?
He spoke. He belittled
her and he laughed at her.
- And she pushed him.
- I believe she's telling the truth.
And I'm certain it'll come
right. Just keep the faith.
Good day.
How stupid of him. To come here
before there was any proof.
Don't be harsh. He meant well.
Meaning well is not enough.
A letter from Rose, to us all.
- How does she sound?
- Hectic and happy.
New York seems to suit her.
M'lord, William Mason's
father is downstairs.
Oh? What does he want?
It seems the owners of the estate
where he's a tenant are selling up.
- What? - The Darnleys
are selling Mallerton?
I find that very hard to believe.
So did he, my Lord, but now
there's to be an auction
of the contents of the house on the tenth.
You astonish me. But what can I do?
He wonders if you could put in a
word for him to keep his tenancy.
How does he know that's
not what they intend?
- He's had a letter giving notice.
- Oh, it may be a formality.
They have to sell with vacant possession,
but the new owners may keep him on.
He just wonders if you could
find out what his chances are.
- Can't he ask them himself?
- You'd be more likely to get an answer.
I hope it's not an impertinence.
No. He was William's father.
He's Daisy's father-in-law.
He enjoys privileges in this house.
That's what I thought, my Lord.
Well, I don't mind telephoning.
Is Mason in the servants' hall?
Give him a drink, and I'll ring
down if I can make contact.
Very good, my Lord.
- So, what are you going to say?
- I've heard they're selling.
I might know someone who's interested,
but I thought I'd check first.
Very ingenious. You would
have made a good courtier.
I would not. Too much standing.
Ah, Mrs Hughes...
You don't think maybe you
should start calling me Elsie?
Not here. Not while we're working.
- Go on, then.
- I wish we could settle the date.
There's no rush, is there?
- Mr Mason. His Lordship's
ringing them now. - Thank you.
But they can't just tell you to go.
Not when you and your dad have
put in so many years there.
They've given me notice, and I
shall have some compensation,
but in the end, I'm
just a tenant, aren't I?
- That's not how I see it.
- It doesn't matter how you see it.
That's how it is.
Hello!
Ah, hello.
Hello, Miss Denker.
What's your mission today?
Not stirring any trouble up, I hope.
- Me? Now, why would you say that?
- I can't imagine (!)
- No, I've come here to sympathise.
- Sympathise? What with?
News that the household here's
to be reduced. I am sorry.
- What? Where did this come from?
- Oh, she never disappoints.
I suppose that's me gone,
then. Last in, first out.
You don't know that.
I suppose it comes down to who's
useful and who's ornamental.
Wouldn't you agree, Mr Barrow?
If it's all right with you, Miss Denker,
I'd rather talk to the organ-grinder.
Oh, dear. I do hope I
haven't cast a shadow.
What did you think you were
doing? Sprinkling sunshine?
- By the way, when did that new
maid start? - What new maid?
She came here with a
message from Her Ladyship.
I haven't the first idea who that c... --
Oh, that's the library.
Mr Mason, you'd better come up with me.
Andrew, what are you doing down here?
- Mr Molesley thought we might need more milk.
- Well, get it, then.
Mr Carson... did you know anything
about staff being laid off?
It's not a subject for the here and now.
Are you ready, Mr Mason?
- Naturally, Sir John is very upset by it all.
- I should think he is.
Unfortunately, they couldn't sell the
estate without vacant possession.
- So, it's sold now?
- Yes. At least, they think so.
- And I have to go.
- Not necessarily.
That would be the
decision of the new owners.
I see. Well...
Thank you very much for
putting in a word, m'lord.
If I hear anything more, I'll
make sure Daisy knows it.
Thank you.
Poor man.
To have his whole future hanging
in the balance, at his time of life.
These are days of uncertainty.
- How was John when you spoke to him?
- In a state.
They're throwing in the towel.
He says, once the debts are paid,
there won't be too much left.
Tim's emigrating to Kenya.
Poor Marian. To be separated
from her only son.
She'll hate that.
- I said we'd go to the sale.
- Do you want to?
Well, John's father and my
papa were as thick as thieves.
It might be nice to find
a memento of the old boy.
How was Granny?
- Getting ready for a fight.
- Run to Mummy, Georgie.
Hello, darling.
I wish you'd stay out of it. Not
least because she's bound to win.
Nobody ever stops her.
What you mean is, no-one
has stopped her YET.
- Can I help you, Miss Denker?
- No.
I'm just tidying Her Ladyship's papers.
She'll be down in a minute.
- I'll tell Mrs Potter.
- Oh, how very reassuring.
The butler giving the
cook an early warning.
What are you talking about?
- No. I don't want to worry you.
- Worry me with what?
Oh, well, if you must know,
there's going to be a shortening
of the wages bill around here.
But why burden ourselves?
What can we do? Que sera, sera.
Are you trying to suggest, in
your usual, maladroit fashion,
that our jobs are in peril?
Well, I hate to sound smug, Mr Spratt,
but I would suggest that Her Ladyship
will always need to dress and undress.
Ooh, while a butler is a luxury?
Is that what you're saying?
My advice, Mr Spratt, is
to live for the moment.
We none of us know what
the future will bring.
Ah, I've put your spectacles
over there, m'lady.
Thank you, Denker. Spratt, I'll
have dinner whenever it's ready.
Would you tell Mrs Potter?
I will, m'lady, although you
could have rung for her yourself.
I beg your pardon?
I was just thinking
aloud, m'lady. I'm sorry.
I was... I was thinking aloud.
Have you decided what to do
if that Miss Bevan returns?
Not yet.
If I pay her, I've a blood-sucking vampire
on my back for the rest of my life.
If I refuse, I'm ruined.
What would you do?
Don't be blackmailed, m'lady.
I know it's easy to say, but don't.
I think I agree. If I'm strong enough.
Either way, my life's up the spout,
and though I hate the idea of scandal,
somehow the shadow of blackmail is worse.
The cheek of her.
It was all I could do
not to give her a slap.
- Will there be anything else?
- No. Thank you.
We may have our problems, the both
of us, but we'll get through them.
- Could you spare me a minute?
- If you like.
Come along to my pantry.
I have a feeling that we
never quite got to the reason
for your visit last night.
No. That's correct.
Only, I'm asking myself...
Were you a messenger from Mrs Hughes?
You could say that, yes.
You were on a mission for her?
Yes. It's true.
Mrs Patmore, did she ask you to
tell me she's changed her mind?
What? No!
Well, not exactly.
I'm waiting.
Well, that is all very fine,
but it's hard for me to
talk about such things.
Now I'm on the edge of my seat.
Oh, it's no good. I
shall have to look away.
You see, she is a very
proud woman, Mr Carson.
I know that, and I respect her for it.
And she would never want to
appear ridiculous in your eyes.
- Nor could she.
- No, but...
as your wife, she wonders
if you would expect...
(.. that she perform her wifely duties.)
Don't wives normally perform their duties?
Good wives, any...
- Oh. - Yes. That's it.
I think we've got there.
I do believe we have.
She needs to know if
that's what you anticipate.
A full marriage.
As opposed to...?
Living together in
companionship, I suppose.
In friendship. Warm friendship, I'm sure.
Is that what she's
offering? Warm friendship?
She has to know what you expect.
Ever think of a time when we're told
the whole Mr Green business is over?
- Of course I do. - We could start
to plan again, revive our dreams.
You mean your old dream of
a house full of children?
I'm sorry.
That's the end of the self-pity. I swear.
If they'll just leave us alone,
I'll be happy, whatever comes.
No, you won't.
At least, not as happy
as you could have been.
But it's nice of you to say it.
Well...
That was an awkward mission
for you, if you like.
Oh, I'll say.
I'm sorry if you're
embarrassed, because I am.
I'm not embarrassed, exactly.
I do not believe that embarrassment
has much of a part to play
when something is as important as this.
But what am I to tell her?
Tell her this, Mrs Patmore.
That, in my eyes, she is beautiful.
I see.
You say she asks if I
want a 'full' marriage...
and the answer is... yes, I do.
I want a real marriage, a true marriage,
with everything that that involves...
.. and I hope I do not ask the indelicate
when I send you back
to relay this message.
Don't worry about me.
I love her, Mrs Patmore.
I am happy and tickled and...
bursting with pride
that she would agree to be my wife.
And I want us to live as
closely as two people can,
for the time that remains to us on earth.
Well, you couldn't make it any clearer.
I'll say that for you.
And if she feels that she must...
.. withdraw...
.. so be it.
But I could never have lived
some... pat-a-cake friendship lie.
No. I didn't think you would.
And for what it's worth, I wish
you the best of luck, Mr Carson.
Thank you, Mrs Patmore.
That is worth a great deal.
I'm sorry to disturb Your Ladyship.
Yes, Spratt. What is it?
I just hope you will be kind enough
to give me sufficient warning.
I'm sorry, what?
So I may find myself alternative
employment, before I am cast out.
Oh, Spratt...
You have clearly had a bad dream
and are confusing it with reality.
Your Ladyship's humour is always a tonic,
but it is a matter of
some importance to me.
If you were talking in Urdu, I
couldn't understand you less.
Miss Denker has broken the news
that the households, here and
at the Abbey, are to be reduced.
- Has she?
- I do not see how you could manage
without a cook, a
housemaid or Miss Denker,
which leaves me as the
only candidate for removal.
Well, I believe many people live
without butlers. So I'm told.
Exactly. And all I ask is some
warning when my time is up.
Well, leave this to me,
Spratt. I will attend to it.
Your Ladyship.
So, can I go to the auction tomorrow?
Well, why does Mr Mason want to go,
himself? Won't it make him sad?
I think he's quite nostalgic.
He's known the family all his life.
- But it's bound to be upsetting.
- Which is why I want to help.
- Oh, I see that.
- And the new owners will be there.
Of course they will. They'll
want to buy a lot of stuff,
to make it convincing when they take over.
We'll be back in time for tea,
so I can do my work for dinner.
- But how will you get there?
- I've asked Mr Stark
if I can ride in the
front of one of the cars.
Well, you've got a nerve!
Mr Carson won't like that.
Even Mr Carson can't
always have it his own way.
- Ooh... - Lady Mary's out, miss, and
I don't know when she'll be back.
Who shall I say has called?
- I'll wait.
- Er...
Lady Mary could be hours, so
there's no point in waiting.
- I will, all the same.
- Thank you, Mr Molesley.
I'll deal with this.
I have no desire to be rude, miss,
but if you wish to see Lady Mary,
I suggest you make an appointment.
What's going on? Carson?
Nothing to concern you, my Lord.
This young lady is leaving.
On the contrary -- it will
concern you quite a lot,
cos I've waited for Lady Mary long enough.
Oh, my dear, how exotic.
I expect to find the whole
of the Bloomsbury Set
curled up in a corner with a book.
Michael knew quite a
few of them, actually.
I met Virginia Woolf in this
room, and Lytton Strachey,
although he didn't stay long.
I wish I'd known your Mr Gregson.
We smiled at each other and
spoke about the weather,
but we never really talked.
Sometimes I feel I've been given
one little bit of happiness,
and that will have to do.
From now on, my life
will be all of a pattern.
Nonsense. You have Marigold.
That's true.
So, what do you think I should do?
- Would you like a London life?
- The fact is, I'd like a life.
Well, I won't speak against London,
but remember, I had no children
to make a country life sensible.
Whereas I have a child
I can't acknowledge.
People aren't so curious in London.
No. They couldn't care less.
Isn't that a relief?
And then there's the museums
and galleries and theatre.
People always talk of such things,
but one only ever goes
when friends come to stay.
- When's your train?
- You're right. We should go.
But the question remains.
What is your future?
Hanging around Downton,
being sniped at by Mary?
Charity work? Travelling?
Publishing? What?
Well, that's the problem. I don't know.
I just don't know.
- I've been watching out for you.
- Why? What is it?
A young woman of most unappealing
aspect has been asking for you.
- Was her name Bevan?
- I knew she was trouble.
She may cause trouble for me, but
only because I've been foolish.
Oh, we can all be foolish, My Lady.
You know, Carson, some day
there'll be something I've done
that even you will condemn me for.
- I doubt that very much.
- Did she say if she'll be back?
She never left. I tried
to get her to go, but --
- Where is she now?
- In the library, with His Lordship.
- Papa, I don't know what this person
has told you... - Only the truth.
.. but I hope you're not giving
her any money. Not on my account.
Take it and go. And remember, one word...
Aren't you the lucky one?
But then I suppose you always are.
- What did she say?
- Enough.
I find I'm most disappointed
in Tony Gillingham.
Don't be.
He wanted us to get married.
Our week in sin was just part
of his plan to persuade me.
Then why did you say no?
Because, when it came
to it, he wasn't right.
At least, not for me.
And you didn't think of George?
Of course I did. I thought of all of you.
I just needed to be sure.
I suppose you were a widow, after all,
and not a deb in her first season.
But it's still not the way your
parents would have behaved.
Oh, I don't know...
If you believe what they
write about the Edwardians.
What were you planning
to do with Miss Bevan?
I wasn't going to be
blackmailed -- I know that.
So I suppose I'd have let
her publish and be damned.
Rather tough on Tony and Mabel.
Anyway, I'll telephone
the bank in the morning
and return your thousand pounds.
I gave her 50 pounds, and here's
her signed confession to blackmail.
How did you manage that?
I told her she could either have
50 pounds, on condition of signing,
or leave with nothing and
be reported to the police.
But... how do you know she won't be back?
I said, if anything were published
or if we ever see her face again,
I'd use it and she'd be prosecuted.
I'm impressed.
My darling Papa transformed
into Machiavelli at a touch.
Will wonders never cease?
Is that a compliment?
You're still out of pocket,
50 quid. I must repay it.
No need. It was money well spent.
- Why?
- To learn that my eldest child
is a child no more and quite
tough enough to run this estate.
Indeed, she could clearly run the kingdom,
should she be called upon to do so.
Well, I hope you mean that.
I do.
And I'm more interested than
ever to see who, in the future,
does come up to your exacting standards.
Maybe no-one.
I'd rather be alone
than with the wrong man.
Who was that young woman I saw leaving?
Someone after money. Usual thing.
- Did you give her any?
- Some.
It was quite a good cause.
- Has Edith telephoned?
- Yes. She'll be home for dinner.
I wonder if she wants to
come to Mallerton tomorrow.
Maybe we should all go. The
Fall Of The House Of Usher.
We mustn't crow. We may be next.
Daisy! Get upstairs. You don't
want to keep them waiting.
I keep thinking of what you told me.
- About what Mr Carson said.
- I should think so. So do I.
I'm sorry I put you through that.
It was difficult, I'll not deny it.
You think I should accept
his terms and set the date?
Oh, no, no. That's your decision.
I can only say he was very
moving when he spoke of you.
He avoided... vulgarity, then?
Vulgarity?
Mr Carson wouldn't be vulgar if
they put him on a seaside postcard.
I'd like to feel a man could
speak of me like that at my age.
I would.
Now, I must get on.
We must get going if we're to
look round before it starts.
So, it's farewell to Mallerton.
Why? Are you planning to turn
up your nose at the new owners?
No. I just don't think
I'll be in Yorkshire
quite so much in the future.
What a funny thing to say.
It's time to go forward,
and I'm unmarried, so I must do it alone.
That sounds rather severe.
I think it sounds very positive.
Thank you, Baxter.
Mr Carson, when you said we'd
know if there was a plan --
Excuse me, while I see them off.
Well, he doesn't seem that
bothered, so it can't be that bad.
You and I both know that the worse it is,
the less he'll want to seem bothered.
Besides, they all want
to be rid of me anyway.
- I'm sure that's not true.
- Yes. Yes, it is.
You've seen how they warn
Andy to keep away from me.
We got on very well when he first arrived,
but now he hardly dares to talk to me.
I think this is all in your head.
No, it's not.
Oh, good. You're here.
I just took a chance.
I thought you might be at
the auction with the others.
I don't like auctions,
especially when I knew
the house in the old days.
I hate to see people's
things piled up in a heap.
Like so much rubbish.
Well, you and I differ when it
comes to the importance of things.
Does it ever get cold on
the moral high ground (?)
I wanted to come because I
don't want us to fall out
over the hospital.
I need to be sure that we can disagree,
without there being any
bad feeling between us.
- Well, it depends who wins.
- Surely not!
Which means you are confident of victory.
Well, we shall see.
Shall I ring for some tea?
It's rather early, but
I think we deserve it.
I remember Mallerton in the 1860s.
Dear old Lady Darnley.
Always liked to stuff
the place with royalty.
She was addicted to curtseying!
How we laughed.
It's sad to think about it.
- Ah, Spratt. Could we have some tea?
- Your Ladyship.
It seemed a little chilly, m'lady,
so I've brought you a shawl.
- Oh, you are a wonder, Denker.
- Thank you.
- I shall miss you.
- M'lady?
Oh, I'm sorry. No, forget I said that.
After all, nothing is settled.
What's not settled?
I don't understand.
I thought you told Spratt
about the staff being cut
back here and at the Abbey.
Well, I... may have mentioned it.
Oh, well. As I said, nothing's decided.
But Your Ladyship couldn't
manage without a maid.
Mrs Crawley does. Don't you?
Indeed I do,
but I don't wish to upset poor Denker.
But Mrs Crawley also manages
without a butler, m'lady.
That is true,
but I don't think I could break
with tradition to quite that degree.
Shall we have some tea?
Your Ladyship.
Miss Denker?
Don't worry, Miss Denker.
I've got a copy of The Lady upstairs.
You don't really mean to manage
without a lady's maid, do you?
Certainly not!
- Then why did you --
- Sometimes it's good to rule by fear.
I can hardly believe it.
I used to come here all the time as a boy.
Sic transit gloria mundi.
Will you be as philosophical
when it's our turn?
Crikey. They're selling everything.
This is John's grandmother,
for God's sake.
They must think it's too large.
Too large for London.
Dear John. We're so sorry.
At least I hope it's what you want.
But it isn't. Not at all.
You're having quite a clean sweep.
We've kept a few portraits to make
a decent show in the London house,
but what's the point of storing the rest?
This life is over for
us. It won't come back.
I admire you. Too many people
just hang on and hang on,
instead of facing things
as they really are.
But we did hang on, I'm afraid.
We hung on for far too long.
And now there's nothing left.
Learn from us.
Ah, there are the Hendersons.
Is there anything you'd like
to buy, or are we just looking?
I wanted to see the house
as much as anything.
I know this hall from
Christmas parties and the like,
but er... I've a mind to poke around.
That were a wedding present
when Sir John got married.
A gift from the tenants. I
contributed half a crown to it.
Had no beer for a week.
Shame to see it sold.
I don't think it's right.
That was for Best of
Breed at the county fair.
Won by a Holstein milker.
My dad tended the Holsteins
before he took over our farm.
It's as if they were selling
your past along with their own.
That's them.
That's the new owners. Mr
and Mrs Philip Henderson.
The ones who won't guarantee
that you can stay on?
- Hey, Daisy. There's no need to --
- I'm not having it. - Daisy!
- It won't do any good.
- I have to say something!
It's not fair!
Who is this person?
She's the daughter-in-law of
one of our tenant farmers.
Excuse me, but are you the new owner?
- I am. - So it's you who
insists on serving notice to men
who've given their whole life to the land?
- Daisy! - You boot out families
who've been here for generations.
- What gives you the right to do that?
- Mrs Mason, there's really no --
I don't think you're the man to tell me.
Pull yourself together. What
do you think you're doing?
A man who sells his wedding presents?
Do you know what it meant for
a farmer to give half a crown?
- Or don't you care?
- Daisy, stop this at once!
I'm sorry, m'lord, but no.
Mr Mason has given his
whole life to this farm,
like his father and
grandfather before him,
but where's the gratitude?
Mr Henderson, I'm sure she
doesn't mean to be rude.
You can't imagine that if I do
keep on some of the tenants,
her father-in-law would now be among them?
Now, please don't be hasty.
She's upset for old Mason --
I'm sorry, Darnley. I don't
find this sort of thing amusing.
Good day, Mrs Mason. You
have not helped your cause.
- I'm speaking for myself, not --
- Good day, Mrs Mason.
Now, will you excuse me?
The auction's starting.
- I'm sure she didn't mean any
- Oh, God. What have I done?
I daresay he'll cool off.
I wouldn't put money on it.
We should find our chairs.
Good afternoon, lords,
ladies and gentlemen.
The first lot consists of
a set of sporting prints
from the mid-19th century. Who
would like to start the bidding?
Two pounds, anyone? Two
pounds to start with.
We're selling things we shouldn't have.
But I kept thinking of that poky
little house in Thurloe Square
- and I couldn't see what else to do.
- You might have stored some of it,
in case one of the children
starts up another house one day.
That's a dream. Face it.
In 20 years' time, there won't be
a house of this size still standing
that isn't an institution.
One pound, seventeen and six. And sold!
That's it.
They're in the drawing room,
they've got coffee and we're done.
- How was your day?
- Not very good.
I'm sure it's not as bad as you
say. Mr Henderson will understand.
No, he won't. I went to help
and I've made things worse.
- This was in front of His Lordship?
- In front of all of them.
- Could prove awkward!
- Thank you, Thomas (!)
If they dismiss me, I've got
no-one but myself to blame.
- It won't come to that, Daisy.
- What will happen to Mr Mason now?
What can he do? Try to find
another farm to take on as tenant,
- but who'll let him at his age?
- It's a good life, though, isn't it?
Are you turning into a country boy?
You'll have to let me show you around.
Andy can find his own way round.
He looks sharp enough to me.
No, no. Come in, come in.
They're here, or they were a minute ago.
Sergeant Willis has something to tell you.
I'm sorry it's late, but I
thought you'd want to hear.
- That depends what it is.
- Shall we go somewhere private?
For God's sake, they've all lived
with this as long as we have.
They've found a witness
to the meeting in the pub.
They've tied them together.
Her confession is real.
This time, it IS over.
- Oh, I can't believe it!
- I shouldn't have come until now.
I'm sorry. I should have waited.
- Never mind that.
- I'll go and tell His Lordship.
You both helped us when all hope was gone,
and I'll not forget it.
I find it hard to acknowledge a
debt but we owe a debt to you.
Justice has triumphed.
I'm not always convinced that
it does, but it has tonight.
We must go down at once.
What can we give them to drink?
It depends how far you want to go, m'lord.
There's some Veuve Cliquot in
a very cool part of the cellar.
It's not iced, of course, but
it would be good to drink.
Fetch it. Fetch three, four
bottles! We must mark this moment.
It's been such a long road. Can
this really be the end of it?
It seems so. And a happy ending!
Anna!
I knew this day would come, I really did.
Everyone, take a glass, quick as you can,
while I propose a toast.
British justice! Envy of the world.
I suppose if it comes
out right in the end.
We could've done with the
result a little sooner.
Amen to that, m'lady.
Andy, Daisy, go and fetch the gramophone.
We never seem to use it
now Lady Rose has gone.
Do we know any more about the
woman who did it, Sergeant Willis?
Only that she sent a message
to Mrs Bates, m'lady.
She says she's sorry for leaving
it so long to take the blame.
- That's all very well --
- Give her a message from me.
Say I forgive her. Wish her luck.
What will they do now?
She'll serve time for
manslaughter. She won't hang.
So Mr Green goes on ruining lives.
But not your life. Not any more.
I'm sorry for what we've
put you through, Mrs Bates.
I probably shouldn't say it, but I am.
You did no more than your
duty, Sergeant Willis.
We'll leave you to it.
Good night. Sleep well.
There's more wine if you finish this.
We'll sleep tonight, all right.
And wake tomorrow without
that rock on our chests.
I think I might go into
Thirsk in the morning,
visit some estate agents.
Start planning again.
But not for a family.
I'm afraid we can't plan for that.
We're free.
We're safe, and I have you.
That's enough, I promise.
I know you want it to be true,
and I love you for it.
So much.
And I love you.
- What are you doing?
- Is this the refrigerator?
It is.
- Mrs Patmore hates it.
- Oh, of course she does.
Don't eat anything
that's meant for tomorrow.
Now, this takes me back.
Did I ever tell you about our
cook when I was a boy, Mrs Yardley?
Many times.
She was quite a crosspatch,
but she was always kind to me.
She used to let me hide down
here when I was in trouble.
She kept a box of biscuits
and sweets just for me.
- Rosamund was furious.
- Rosamund was jealous.
Come to bed.
Sorry, Carson. We shouldn't be here.
Oh, quite all right, m'lady.
But I did want a private word
on the question of Daisy.
I've heard what happened at the auction.
I don't believe we can
allow it to go unnoticed.
- No, I suppose not.
- It is a dismissible offence.
Oh, isn't that a bit harsh? On
the day of Bates' good news?
I'm sure she regrets it.
I daresay Guy Fawkes regretted
trying to blow up Parliament,
m'lady, but he still had to pay the price.
Can't you just tick her off?
You'll know how to ensure
there's no repetition.
Very good, m'lady, if
that's what you wish.
We're going up. Good night.
Good night, m'lord, m'lady.
Have you thought about where
the Carsons will live?
- After they're married?
- Not really.
I'd rather put it out of my mind.
Will we have to call her Mrs Carson?
I'm not sure I can.
We have higher mountains to climb.
Have you come to a decision
about the hospital?
What sort of a decision?
I suppose I hope you can support
Mama's efforts to keep control.
Better yet, stay out of it entirely.
I can't stay out of it,
Robert. It's too important.
And your mother, incidentally, is wrong.
All of which adds up to a very
trying spring and summer ahead.
I suppose you thought
there'd be no repercussions,
what with Mr Bates' news.
No. I knew I hadn't heard the last of it.
I just want to know how bad it'll be.
Bad enough, I hope, to make you
feel small and foolish and immature,
and unable to control your
feelings in an adult manner.
I feel all those things already.
But not bad enough for
you to lose your place.
If it were up to me,
it might be different.
But Her Ladyship insisted
on a second chance.
- Thank you, Mr Carson.
- Don't thank me, thank her.
Now, get back to the party
before I change my mind.
Right, well, shall we rejoin the others?
Before we do...
.. I know I've been putting you off...
.. and Mrs Patmore spoke
of your conversation.
I knew she would.
I hope we've not shocked you between us.
No, I'm not shocked.
I thought it better to be honest.
Once you'd raised the matter.
I agree. Much better.
I wouldn't want you to think
that I'd inveigled you
into an arrangement which
was not what you'd expected.
I would never think that.
Right.
Well, if you've had second thoughts,
I think we should let the
staff know in the morning.
I won't make a big announcement.
We'll just tell one or two people
and let it come out naturally.
There'll be a bit of a nine
days' wonder, of course,
but we'll get over it.
But you misunderstand me.
I was afraid I'd be a
disappointment to you.
That I couldn't hope to
please you as I am now.
But if you're sure...
I have never been so sure of anything.
Well, then, Mr Carson...
If you want me, you can have me.
To quote Oliver Cromwell, warts and all.
I don't want to be a servant on
my wedding day. Is that so wrong?
The battle lines are drawn,
now we must fight it out.
- I hope you are not implying she would
be more powerful than I. - Oh, no, indeed.
Mary took Marigold to
the Drewes' farm today.
When a woman loves a child,
it must stay with her.
As you're aware, this is
the day of the Malton Show.
Does it ever occur to you
that you might be wrong?